<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://cwrc.ca/templates/css/tei.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to Congress from Elizabeth Cady Stanton, Susan B. Anthony and Others
					in Support of Women's Right to Vote in the United States, 1871</title>
				<author>Elizabeth Cady Stanton </author>
					<author>Isabella Beecher Hooker </author>
					<author>Elizabeth S. Bladen</author> 
					<author>Olympia Brown </author>
					<author>Susan B. Anthony </author>
					<author>Josephine S. Griffing</author>
				<respStmt>
					<name>
						<orgName>(U.S.) National Archives</orgName>
					</name>
					<resp>Publisher</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>National Archives</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Public Domain</licence>
				</availability>
					<idno type="custom">National Archives Identifier https://catalog.archives.gov/id/1634184</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This primary source comes from the Records of the U.S. Senate. National Archives
					Identifier: 1634184 Full Citation: Letter to the United States Congress from
					Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B. Anthony and Others in Support of Women's
					Suffrage; 12/1871; Petition and Memorials, Resolutions of State Legislatures,
					and Related Documents which were Referred to the Committee on the Judiciary
					during the 42nd Congress; (SEN 42A-H11.4); Committee Papers, 1816 - 2011;
					Records of the U.S. Senate, Record Group 46; National Archives Building,
					Washington, DC. [Online Version,
					https://www.docsteach.org/documents/document/congress-stanton-anthony, last accessed 19 February 2023]</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>This encoded file was created by Diane Jakacki and made available for a Linked
					Editing Academic Framework (LEAF) / LEAF-Writer workshop. This file is not meant for
					use or publication outside of the workshop environment.</p>
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/leaf_workshops/main/exercises/Congress_Letter/congress_letter_image1.jpg"/>

			<opener>To the Honorable the Senate and House of Representatives of the United States in
				Congress Assembled:</opener>
			<p>The undersigned, Citisens of the United States, believing that under the present
					Federal Constitution all women who are citisens of the United States have the
					right to vote, pray your Honorable Body to
				enact a law during the present session that shall assist and protect them in the exercise of that
					right
			</p>
			<p>And they pray further that they may be permitted in person, and in behalf of the
				thousands of other women who are petitioning Congress to the same effect to be heard
				upon this Memmoiral before the Senate and House at an early day in the present
				Session.</p>
			<p>We ask your Honorable Body to bear in mind that while men are represented on the
				floor of Congress and so may be said to be heard there, women
				who are allowed no vote and therefore no representation cannot truly be heard except
				as Congress shall open its doors to us in person.</p>
			<closer>
				<signatures>Elizabeth Cady Stanton 
				Isabella Beecher Hooker 
				Elizabeth S. Bladen 
				Olympia Brown 
				Susan B. Anthony 
				Josephine S. Griffing</signatures> 
				Hartford Conn. Dec. 1871</closer>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
